So, the possibility of explaining the mysteries of gravity and of discovering extra dimensions of space -- perhaps now you get a sense as to why thousands of physics geeks collectively lost their cool over our little, two-photon bump. A discovery of this type would rewrite the textbooks. But remember, the message from us experimentalists that actually were doing this work at the time, was very clear: we need more data. With more data, the little bump will either turn into a nice, crisp Nobel Prize -- (Laughter) Or the extra data will fill in the space around the bump and turn it into a nice, smooth line. So we took more data, and with five times the data, several months later, our little bump turned into a smooth line. The news reported on a "huge disappointment," on "faded hopes," and on particle physicists "being sad." Given the tone of the coverage, you'd think that we had decided to shut down the LHC and go home. (Laughter) But that's not what we did. But why not? I mean, if I didn't discover a particle -- and I didn't -- if I didn't discover a particle, why am I here talking to you? Why didn't I just hang my head in shame and go home? Particle physicists are explorers. And very much of what we do is cartography. Let me put it this way: forget about the LHC for a second. Imagine you are a space explorer arriving at a distant planet, searching for aliens. What is your first task? To immediately orbit the planet, land, take a quick look around for any big, obvious signs of life, and report back to home base. That's the stage we're at now. We took a first look at the LHC for any new, big, obvious-to-spot particles, and we can report that there are none. We saw a weird-looking alien bump on a distant mountain, but once we got closer, we saw it was a rock. But then what do we do? Do we just give up and fly away? Absolutely not; we would be terrible scientists if we did. No, we spend the next couple of decades exploring, mapping out the territory, sifting through the sand with a fine instrument, peeking under every stone, drilling under the surface. New particles can either show up immediately as big, obvious-to-spot bumps, or they can only reveal themselves after years of data taking. Humanity has just begun its exploration at the LHC at this big high energy, and we have much searching to do. But what if, even after 10 or 20 years, we still find no new particles? We build a bigger machine. (Laughter) We search at higher energies. Planning is already underway for a 100-kilometer tunnel that will collide particles at 10 times the energy of the LHC. We don't decide where nature places new particles. We only decide to keep exploring. But what if, even after a 100-kilometer tunnel or a 500-kilometer tunnel or a 10,000-kilometer collider floating in space between the Earth and the Moon, we still find no new particles? Then perhaps we're doing particle physics wrong. (Laughter) Perhaps we need to rethink things. Maybe we need more resources, technology, expertise than what we currently have. We already use artificial intelligence and machine learning techniques in parts of the LHC, but imagine designing a particle physics experiment using such sophisticated algorithms that it could teach itself to discover a hyperdimensional graviton. But what if? What if the ultimate question: What if even artificial intelligence can't help us answer our questions? What if these open questions, for centuries, are destined to be unanswered for the foreseeable future? What if the stuff that's bothered me since I was a little kid is destined to be unanswered in my lifetime? Then that ... will be even more fascinating. We will be forced to think in completely new ways. We'll have to go back to our assumptions, and determine if there was a flaw somewhere. And we'll need to encourage more people to join us in studying science since we need fresh eyes on these century-old problems. I don't have the answers, and I'm still searching for them. But someone -- maybe she's in school right now, maybe she's not even born yet -- could eventually guide us to see physics in a completely new way, and to point out that perhaps we're just asking the wrong questions. Which would not be the end of physics, but a novel beginning. Thank you. (Applause)
Por lo tanto, la posibilidad de explicar los misterios de la gravedad y de descubrir las dimensiones extraespaciales... tal vez ahora se dan una idea de por qué miles de frikis de la física perdieron colectivamente la calma ante la pequeña protuberancia de dos fotones. Un descubrimiento de este tipo sería reescribir los libros de texto. Pero recuerden, nuestro mensaje como experimentadores que hacían este trabajo en el momento, fue muy claro: necesitamos más datos. Con más datos, la pequeña protuberancia bien podría convertirse en un premio Nobel en ciernes, (Risas) O los datos adicionales deberán rellenar el espacio alrededor de la protuberancia y convertirla en una línea agradable y suave. Así que tomamos más datos, y cinco veces más datos, varios meses después, nuestra pequeña protuberancia se había convertido en una línea suave. La noticia informó una "gran decepción" de "esperanzas marchitas," y de "la tristeza de los físicos de partículas". Teniendo en cuenta el tono de la cobertura, se podría pensar que habíamos decidido cerrar el colisionador y volver a casa. (Risas) Pero eso no es lo que hicimos. ¿Pero por qué no? Es decir, si no he descubierto una partícula, y no lo hice, si no he descubierto una partícula, ¿por qué estoy aquí hablando con Uds.? ¿Por qué no se me cae la cara de vergüenza y vuelvo a casa? Los físicos de partículas somos exploradores. Y mucho de lo que hacemos es cartografiar. Lo pondré de esta manera: olvídense del colisionador por un segundo. Imaginen que son exploradores espaciales que llegan a un planeta distante, a la búsqueda de extraterrestres. ¿Cuál es su primera tarea? Para orbitar de inmediato el planeta, aterrizar, echar un vistazo alrededor en busca de signos evidentes de la vida, e informar a la base. Esa es la etapa que estamos ahora. Echamos un primer vistazo en el colisionador buscando partículas nuevas, grandes, obviamente detectables, y podemos informar que no hay ninguna. Vimos una protuberancia extraña de aspecto raro en una montaña lejana, pero al acercarnos, vimos que era una roca. Pero entonces, ¿qué hacemos? ¿Nos damos por vencidos y nos vamos? Por supuesto que no. Seríamos científicos terribles si nos rindiéramos. No, pasamos las siguientes dos décadas explorando, cartografiando el territorio, tamizando la arena con un instrumento fino, mirando debajo de cada piedra, perforando la superficie. Nuevas partículas pueden mostrar ya sea de inmediato protuberancias grandes, evidentes, o pueden revelarse tras años de toma de datos. La humanidad acaba de comenzar su exploración con el colisionador, en este coloso de alta energía, y tenemos mucho que hacer. Pero ¿y si, incluso tras 10 o 20 años, seguimos sin encontrar nuevas partículas? Construimos una máquina más grande. (Risas) Buscamos con energías mayores. Buscamos con altas energías. Están planeadas para un túnel de 100 km que colisionará partículas a 10 veces la energía del LHC. No decidimos donde la naturaleza coloca nuevas partículas. Solo decidimos seguir explorando. Pero ¿y si, incluso tras construir un túnel de 100 km o un túnel de 500 km o un colisionador de 10 000 km que flote en el espacio entre la Tierra y la luna, seguimos sin encontrar nuevas partículas? Entonces, tal vez estamos explorando mal la física de partículas. (Risas) Tal vez tenemos que volver a pensar las cosas. Tal vez necesitamos más recursos, tecnología, experiencia, que lo que tenemos actualmente. Ya usamos técnicas de aprendizaje automático y de inteligencia artificial en algunas partes del colisionador, pero imaginen el diseño de un experimento de física de partículas que usa algoritmos sofisticados que podrían autoaprender para descubrir un gravitón hiperdimensional. ¿Pero y si...? ¿Qué pasa si, en última instancia, la inteligencia artificial no nos ayuda a responder nuestras preguntas? ¿Y si estas preguntas durante siglos no resueltas, no tuvieran respuestas en un futuro inmediato? ¿Y si las cosas que me molestaban desde niño están destinadas a no tener respuestas en el transcurso de mi vida? Entonces... eso será aún más fascinante. Nos veremos obligados a pensar en formas completamente nuevas. Tendremos que volver a nuestras suposiciones, y determinar si hay un defecto en alguna parte. Y necesitaremos para animar a más gente unirnos en el estudio de la ciencia ya que necesitamos una mirada nueva sobre estos problemas centenarios. No tengo las respuestas y aún estoy en busca de ellas. Pero alguien, tal vez ella está en la escuela en este momento, tal vez ella ni siquiera ha nacido todavía, podría finalmente guiarnos para ver la física de forma completamente nueva, e indicarnos que tal vez estamos haciendo las preguntas equivocadas. Lo que no sería el fin de la física, sino el comienzo de una novela. Gracias. (Aplausos)